准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
谁怕钳老板
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
分镜总监
指导总监
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
海之霸
差不多要好了  凯伦
It's almost ready, Karen
随时都会好
Any minute now
出来了
There it is
你看见没  凯伦
Did you see that, Karen?
爱.exe
你就不能干啥正经点的事吗
Don't you have anything better to do?
还能干啥
Like what?
都已经好几个月没客人了
We haven't had a customer in months
凯伦  那是什么
Karen, what is that?
好像是个
I think it's a
客人
customer
我该怎么办
What should I do?
问他要不要点餐
Ask him if he wants to order something
感觉他不会点  不过我尽力
Sounds unlikely, but I'll try
菜单
先生好
Hello, sir
你不是真的想点餐吧
You don't actually want to order anything, do you?
有没有不带海霸糊的食物
Do you have any food without chum?
我们没有
No, we do not
那就来杯咖啡好了
Well, I'll just have a cup of coffee
咖啡里面没海霸糊吧
There's no chum in coffee, right?
没没  当然没了
Oh no, no, of course not
章鱼哥
Squidward?
你来干嘛
What are you doing here?
给老螃蟹当间谍吗
Spying for Krabs?
你真以为我是来偷你海霸糊秘方的吗
Do you really think I'm here
to steal your secret chum formula?
在理
Good point
那你干嘛来
Then why are you here?
我要找个宁静祥和
I needed a nice quiet place
又无人问津的地方
that's completely devoid of life
来完成我的舞台剧本
to finish writing my stage play
舞台剧吗
A play, huh?
什么剧情
What's it about?
剧情是一个才貌双全的艺术家
It tells the story of a handsome and talented artist
顽强抵抗他邪恶的老板
who struggles against his evil employer
一只乖戾粗鲁的螃蟹  名叫钳老板
an angry, uncouth crab named Mr. Snippers
开头写好了
I have the beginning worked out
结尾想不出来怎么写
but I just can't figure out the ending
真巧啊
What a coincidence
我正好也在写剧本
I happen to be writing a play too
海之霸
讲的是只暴怒大螃蟹
It's about a big angry crab
他老是折磨一个善良无辜的店长
who torments a nice innocent shopkeeper
可我只写好了结尾
But I only have the ending
真美啊
It's beautiful
这就是命运
This is destiny
我们一定要一起出演咱俩的剧
We must put on our play, together
幸好我早就搭好舞台了
Luckily, I've already built a stage
不错  不过得改一下
Not bad, but we simply have to change
这幕布的颜色
the color of this curtain
就比如改成这个优美的猩红色
To this lovely shade of scarlet, for instance
应该要绯红  不要猩红
It should be crimson, not scarlet
简直丑死了
That's hideous
你鼻子才丑死了
Your nose is hideous
听起来你们俩得定个导演
Sounds like you two need a director
真是好办法
Excellent idea
我正是导演的不二之选
Of course, I'm the obvious choice for director
得了吧  我可喜欢肆意使唤别人了
Oh please, I love bossing people around
应该让我当导演
I should be the director
对对对
Yeah
你来当那就肯定搞砸
If we want it ruined
白痴
Cretin
混蛋
Jerk
够了
Enough
既然你们两个达不成共识
Since you two can't agree on anything
那就我负责导演
I'll be the director
这一幕呢
Now, in this scene
钳老板在痛斥他的员工们
Mr. Snippers is berating his employees
逼着他们划一艘古罗马战舰
as they row a Roman galley
给我回去工作
Get back to work
你们这群懒
you lazy--
回去工作  你们这群懒
Back to work, you lazy--
等一下
Hold it
里面肯定有误会
I think there's been a mistake
我演钳老板才对
I am playing Mr. Snippers
你说什么鬼话
What are you talking about?
钳老板这个角色正适合我
I'm perfect for the role of Mr. Snippers
众所周知  反派戏份才最出彩
And everyone knows the villain is the best part
只有一个办法
There's only one way to settle this
你们都得试镜
You'll both have to audition
试就试
If I must
这么说吧
I will say
反正光演自己的角色我也不咋适应
I am not accustomed to reading for my roles anymore
就直接演绎经典名著集锦得了
I shall read from a medley of classics
罗蜊欧  罗蜊欧
Clameo, Clameo
[ 改自《罗密欧与朱丽叶》
“罗蜊欧”改回“罗密欧”即为原句 ]
为什么你偏偏是罗蜊欧呢
wherefore art thou, Clameo?
各位朋友
Friends
[ 出自《凯撒大帝》 ]
各位罗马人
Romans
各位同胞
Countrymen
请你们听我说
Lend me your ears
耳朵借我
我总是指望陌生人的愚蠢
I have always relied on the idiocy of strangers
[ 改自《欲望号街车》
“愚蠢”改回“慈悲”即为原句 ]
我本来可以拥有蟹黄堡
I could'a had Krabby Patties
[ 改自《码头风云》
原句为“我本来可以往上爬” ]
我本来能偷到秘方
I could'a had the formula
[ 改自《码头风云》
原句为“我本来能是竞争者” ]
不该只有海霸糊
Instead of chum
[ 改自《码头风云》
原句为“不该是个没用的家伙” ]
而我现在正是这副德行
Which is all I have
[ 出自《码头风云》 ]
戏精一个
What a ham
你才戏精呢
You're the one chewing the scenery
住手
Hold it
我选好了
I've made my choice
演钳老板的演员
The role of Mr. Snippers goes to
不可能让你们当
neither of you
得选别人来演钳老板
We'll cast someone else to play Mr. Snippers
是吗
Oh yeah?
你要上哪找演员啊
Where are you gonna find an actor
而且还要既听话  又笨到能免费干活
who will follow orders
and is dumb enough to do it for free?
去旧蛤山的公交是在这里等吗
Is this where I catch the bus to Clam Francisco?
蟹老板警告过我
Mr. Krabs did warn me
别在便宜货超市连续左转三次  小子
Never make three left turns at the Barg'N-Mart, boy-o
钳老板的演员找到了
We found our Mr. Snippers
海绵宝宝  你来演反派
Now SpongeBob, you'll be playing the villain
众所周知  反派戏份才最出彩
Everyone knows the villain is the best part
从第56页开始演吧
Let's pick it up from page 56
速速去工作
Getteth to worketh
不然我就要碰碰你们萌萌的鼻子了
or I'm gonna giveth you a boop on your cutesy noseth
碰碰
Boop
不对不对
No, no, no
要这样
Like this
速速去工作  不然我就打扁你们
Getteth to work or I'll clobbereth thou
然后你就用鼓槌打他们
And then you hit 'em with your drumsticks
对
Yeah
要像这样
Like this
不对  要像这样
No, no, like this
用力点
Harder
海绵宝宝  怎么了
SpongeBob, what's the matter?
干嘛不照着剧本去演
Why aren't you following the script?
你不觉得钳老板他太
Don't you think Mr. Snippers is too
坏了吗
mean?
演个舞台剧而已
It's just a play
剧里不念台词的话
And in a play, if you don't read the lines
那就等于是工作没做好
you'll be doing a bad job
你想把工作做好对不对  海绵宝宝
You want to do a good job, don't you, SpongeBob?
对
Yeah
对对
Yeah, yeah
对
Yeah
那就好好演起来吧
Now do some good acting
快演  乖狗狗
Act, boy
演吧
Act
速速去工作  不然我就打扁你们
Getteth to worketh or I'll clobbereth thee
海神王在上  他应该是懂了
By Neptune, I think he's got it
谁怕钳老板
感谢
Thank you
观剧愉快
Enjoy the show
你说老螃蟹会过来丢人现眼吗
Do you think Krabs will show up for his humiliation?
会来的
He'll be here
我给他免费送了张票呢
I sent him a free ticket
给我让开
Outta the way
借过一下
Coming through
VIP来了
VIP here
尤金
Eugene
你能来  我可真高兴啊
So glad you could make it
好好好
Yeah, yeah
这场免费舞台剧最好值回票价
This free play better be worth the money
放心
Don't worry
该遭的报应总会来的
you'll get everything that's coming to you
遭什么了
What was that?
这边请  先生
Right this way, sir
谁怕钳老板
Who's Afraid of Mr. Snippers
编剧  章鱼哥
written by Squidward Tentacles?
以及谢尔顿痞老板
And also Sheldon J. Plankton?
放第一位的应该是我才对
I should get top billing
谁都别想踩我谢尔顿
No one stands taller than Sheldon J.--
痞老板
Plankton
速速去工作
Gett-eth to work-eth
你们可谓愚中惰者之最
Thou-est are the laziest of fools-eth
外面的海报我都看到了  章鱼哥
I saw that poster outside, Squidward
你喜欢不
Did you like it?
不喜欢
No
因为呢  写第一个的应该是我的名字
For one thing it should read "Plankton and Squidward"
得了吧
Oh, please
剧本大部分是我写的
I did most of the writing
你们为何不工作了
Why-est art thou not worketh-ing?
虽然我很喜欢
As much as I like
看痞老板跟章鱼哥遭报应
to see Plankton and Squidward get what's coming to 'em
但这个钳老板的人设也太恶毒了
I think this Mr. Snippers character is a real jerk
当反派可真累啊
Being a villain is hard work
职员表霸占狂
Credit hog
江郎才尽臭写手
Washed up hack
臭写手
Hack?
差不多得了
Alright, that's it
给我下去
Get off of me
他跑我罗马长袍里了
He's in my toga
放开
Let go
如你所愿
As you wisheth
演员啊
Actors
就爱即兴发挥
They love improv
残废还是健全
To maim or not to maim
[ 改自《哈姆雷特》 ]
这是个值得考虑的问题
that is the question
好
Yeah
好  打他
Yeah, hit him
用力点打
Hit him harder
别再闹了
Stop this madness
什么
What?
拜托
Come on
烂
Boo
让我们别再打了
Let us not fight
难道我们不都是海洋生物吗
Are we not all creatures of the sea?
事实就是  你们两位的相似之处
The truth is, you're both more alike
多于你们的不同之处
than you are different
我深信  你们内心深处依旧相亲相爱
I'm sure deep down you actually love each other
了不起
Good for you
真美啊
So beautiful
那个抢镜头的小鬼
Why, that little scene-stealer
我们才不相亲相爱
We do not love each other
但我们倒是有一样共识
But we do agree on one thing
加油打倒他
Yeah, get him, boys
打倒那个暴君钳老板
Take that tyrant Mr. Snippers down
能看到你们俩好好相处  我可真高兴
I'm just happy to see you two getting along
好痒啊
That tickles
好看
Brilliant
太神了
Amazing
真是跌宕起伏
What an emotional roller-coaster
谁想去蟹堡王一起开余兴派对啊
Who wants to go to the after-party at the Krusty Krab?
余兴派对价格翻倍
After-party prices are doubled
章鱼哥  你负责收银
Squidward, you're running the register
速速回去工作  你个懒鬼
Get to work, you lazy bum
钳老板说的就是这么个台词  对吧
That's what Mr. Snippers would say, ain't it?
晚安  晚安
Good night, good night--
[ 出自《罗密欧与朱丽叶》 ]
离别是这样甜蜜的凄清
Parting is such sweet sorrow
珊氏鱼
编剧
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
指导总监
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
啊  大海
Ah, the ocean
那么生机勃勃
So bustling with aquatic life
那么
So
潮湿
wet
来了一只最为神出鬼没的海洋生物
Here comes one of the most elusive of sea creatures now
松鼠
the squirrel
你好  海绵宝宝
Howdy, SpongeBob
可不可以帮忙给点意见
Could you give me some feedback
评价我写的这份学术论文
on this scientific paper I'm writing?
当然可以了  珊迪
I'd love to, Sandy
海洋布满了形形色色的水生生物
"The ocean is permeated
with a multitude of aquatic life
从六斑玉筋鱼
from the Ammodytes hexapterus
再到海星纲与多孔动物门  无所不有
to the Asteroidea and the Porifera
[ 多孔动物门：含海绵 ]
生物之间虽然表面上存在着差异
Though the differences are ostensible
但仍有大量相似之处
there is a plethora of similarities"
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
没事吧
Are you alright?
你的科学论文
Your science paper
冷冰冰的
so cold
全是说教
so d-d-didactic
天啊  你觉得
Gosh, do you reckon
里面专业内容太多了吗
it's too heavy on the technical side?
感觉完完全全不同于
It doesn't sound like anything
我体验到的美妙海洋生活
I've experienced living in this wonderful ocean
既没描绘出暖流拂面的感觉
It doesn't capture the feel
of a warm current in your face
又没捕捉到海草轻触脚趾间的感觉
or what kelp feels like between your toes
真希望你也能跟我一样体验海洋生活
I wish you could experience the ocean like I do
珊迪  话说你这是想要
So, Sandy, what was it that you wanted to
你来得正好
You're just in time
隆重推出  我的化鱼机
Presenting my Fish-U-Up Machine
用这设备
With this device
可以把我的松鼠DNA跟鱼类DNA互换
I'll swap out my squirrel DNA with fish DNA
等换完  我就可以在水里面呼吸了
And then I'll be able to breathe water
还能跟海洋生物一样亲身研究海洋
Then, I can study the ocean like y'all sea critters do
再也不用穿笨重的潜水服了
Without my bulky old suit on
感谢咱帅气的志愿者弗雷德大方相助
All thanks to the generous help
of our handsome volunteer, Fred
等下
Wait
我不是来这理头发的吗
I thought I was getting a haircut
按按钮吧  小方块
Boop that button, square dude
按
Boop
成功了
It really worked
你长鳃了
You have gills
我先带你出去呼吸新鲜海水
Let's get you a breath of fresh water
海洋很壮丽吧
Isn't the ocean grand?
就让海水轻轻流过你的鳃
Let it flow through your gills
不好
Oh no
珊迪  相信你的鳃
Sandy, trust in your gills
呼吸
Breathe
海绵宝宝
Hey, SpongeBob
珊迪又忘了怎么呼吸是吧
Sandy forgot how to breathe, huh?
我也老是会忘
Happens to me all the time
我会在水里呼吸了
I'm a water breather
鱼类的习性我还得学不少呢
There's a lot I need to learn about the way of the fish
对啊  就比如说别吸入黄色的水
Yeah, like, don't breathe the yellow water
现在我全身精力充沛得不得了了
Now I feel more spry than a springtime pup
要先来干什么呢  海绵宝宝
What should we do first, SpongeBob?
那我就建议
Might I suggest
全都来
everything
港口公厕
鱼类内急
解放站
水母田
你说得对
You were right
爪子触碰青草真舒服啊
this grass feels so good on my paws
没穿潜水服  感觉蜇得更疼了
Those stings hurt extra without my diving suit on
还有点爽
It's kind of invigorating
快来
Come on
蜇我
Sting me
我就在这边
I'm right here
放马过来
Bring it on
珊迪
Sandy
来看这个
Check this out
感受水母田之美
Feel the glory of Jellyfish Fields
真美啊
It's beautiful
折射过来的阳光
And the refracted sunlight
直接照耀在我皮毛上的感觉真舒服
feels so good on my bare fur
来深吸一口洋流
And just breathe in that current
珊迪  你脱毛了
Sandy, you're shedding
还长了鳞片
And you've got scales
我的天啊  还真是
Good golly, I am and I do
我的鱼类属性越来越凸显出来了
More of my new fish-type attributes
are making themselves known
不知道我还有啥鱼类特点
I wonder what other fish traits I have
说不定我游泳技术可高超了
Maybe I got swimming skills
只有一个地方能确认
There's only one place to find out
闻闻那四处弥漫的咸味啊
Smell that salty waft
那还等什么呢  我的鱼类朋友
Well, what are we waiting for, my fish friend?
炮来了
Cannonball
海洋生物热爱水很棒吧  珊迪
Isn't it nice how sea creatures take to water, Sandy?
珊迪
Sandy
只摸到了她的毛
It's just her pelt I felt
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
珊迪
Sandy
你全身都是鳞片了
You're all scales
你看看
Well, look at that
我好自在
I feel so free
我可以四处灵活滑水了
I can glide through the water like a greased pig
说起来  我有点饿了
Speaking of, I feel hungry
附近的鱼类居民都吃什么啊
What do fish folk eat around these parts?
那你可走运了
You're in luck
酷乐湖有全海底最棒的海滩无证小摊
Goo Lagoon has the best
unlicensed beach vendors under the sea
你说无证  我倒想试试看了
You had me at "unlicensed"
来份最好的鱼食小片片  大好人
Your finest fish flakes, my good man
随你便
Whatever
吃吧
Dig in
这吃法还挺巧妙
Oh, well, ain't that clever
你们吃小片片还花钱啊
You guys pay for your flakes?
要吃不
Want some?
谢了
Thanks
我刚吃过
but I just ate
并且咱还得回去呢
Besides, we need to head back
变鱼真是让我大开眼界啊
Being a fish has given me all kinds of insights
你只管写你的  珊迪
Just keep writing, Sandy
咱
We--
这就带你回家
we'll get you home
你什么毛病  海绵宝宝
What's gotten into you, SpongeBob?
你表现简直是大惊小怪得不得了
You're acting more skittish than a long-tailed cat
in a roomful of rocking chairs
亮晶晶的钩子看着真好吃
Those shiny hooks look delicious
珊迪  不要
Sandy, no
珊迪  离那些钩子远一点
Sandy, stay away from those
可它们好
But they're so
诱人
inviting
珊迪
Sandy
不要咬钩啊
Don't take the bait
珊迪
Sandy
快过来
Come to papa
好
Alright
来给我看一眼
Now let's take a look at you
我的天啊
Oh, goodness
你自己也没好到哪里去
You ain't no prize yourself, mister
附近的水里都倒了些什么玩意
What are they dumping in the water around here?
珊迪
Sandy
你没事了
You're safe
抱歉  海绵宝宝
Sorry, SpongeBob
不小心被鱼类天性冲昏头了
I let my fish side get the better of me
珊迪
Sandy?
你用科学给自己改造过度了
You over-scienced yourself
得带你回实验室
Let's get you back to your lab
不好
Oh no
她退化了
She's devolved
必须救她
I gotta help her
珊迪  回来
Sandy, come back
珊迪
Sandy
不要伤害小蜗
Leave Gary alone
不要
No
小蜗
Gary
小蜗  你没事
Gary, you're safe
可是等下  那珊迪是在吃什么
But, wait, then what is Sandy eating?
布丁杯
Pudding cups?
小蜗  你又往壳里私藏布丁了吗
Gary, have you been hoarding those in your shell again?
等一下
Wait a minute
布丁
pudding
壳
shell
家
home
树屋
dome
对了
that's it
珊迪很有可能在树屋里藏了解药
Maybe Sandy's hoarding antidotes back in her dome
布丁的事等会再算账  小不点
We'll discuss this pudding thing later, young man
珊迪  不要
Sandy, no
珊迪
Sandy
走了很多里路后
珊迪肯定在哪有解药
Sandy's gotta have a remedy somewhere
在哪
Where is it?
好了
There
泡泡浴
Bubble bath
珊迪最近闻着可不大对头
Sandy has been smelling a little fishy lately
有 鱼 腥 味
现在  重新进化血清
And now, the re-evolution serum
找到了
That's it
进化过头了
Too far
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
你出手转危为安了
You saved the day
真高兴一切都恢复正常了
I'm just glad everything's back to normal
对啊  不过感觉好像忘了什么
Yeah, but I feel like we forgot something
我的腿
My legs
我的大毛腿
My furry, furry legs
我的毛腿
My furry legs
啊对
Oh, right
弗雷德
Fred
我去拿提篮来
I'll get the carrier